בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is עין ג', ayin gimmel,
73. We are smack at our דף, daf, right? That's a good
point. We're smack in the middle of some of the really intense
סוגיות sugyas in ש"ס shas about עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. We just
had a great debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava whether עדים
זוממים למפרע הוא נפסל edim zomemim lemafre'a hu nifsul or מכאן ולהבא
הוא נפסל. mikan ule'haba hu nifsul. אביי Abaye says I guess the
intuitive thing, which is, you know, once you're proven here that they
were lying and you trust the זוממים, zomemim, then we know that
back here when they testified they were lying, so in the
interim they're they're פסול עדים. pasul edim. Which again doesn't mean that
we assume just because they lied once they're going to lie again,
but what it means is because they bore false testimony that labels
them as רשעים rasha'im and that or as עדים זוממים, edim zomemim,
and that in that and from a formal sense invalidates their testimony,
even if what they were saying was true.
Well, you can't because רבא's Rava response is no, only from this
point forward. One explanation is a very fascinating approach in עדים זוממים.
edim zomemim. Logically there's no reason we believe the later group. So
if the תורה Torah tells us to, fine, we will, but to
the degree that we can actually say that proves that they were
lying, we can't say. We just say we take the תורה's Torah
status and the תורה Torah declares them as עדים זוממים, edim zomemim,
but we don't sort of know as a fact that they were
lying. So that status is going to be from that point on.
And if you want to say that status is we believe that
they have testified falsely because there's not a good logic to believe
it, we're only going to believe it if you tell me so,
I'll believe it. Okay, so we're only going to believe it from
this point forward. That's a very nice conceptual way of thinking about
עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, right? But the other way he says, nah,
I really agree to אביי, Abaye, it's back here, but as Micah
was saying, then everybody, you're never going to know anybody you're going
to use to sign your documents. They might be found out two
years later to be עדים זוממים edim zomemim and all those documents
will be invalid. So from a pragmatic point of view, certainly when
it comes to monetary documents, you know, you can't sort of validate
them if they were good, if they were used for like, you
know, personal status issues. But if it comes to monetary documents, we
can say that it's going to be כשר kosher just to protect
people. But anyway, the הלכה halakha is this is one of the
cases we פוסקין pasken like אביי Abaye and we פוסקין pasken that
למפרע הוא נפסל. lemafre'a hu nifsul. Yes, Micah.
My question also is like, for instance, in מסכת סנהדרין, Masechet Sanhedrin,
you can get out, you can, you know, regain your status once
you destroy or whatever it is.
Yeah, so Jenna asked that. Yeah, I mean, there's always possibility of
תשובה. teshuvah. Even from עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, there's a possibility of
תשובה. teshuvah. So the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin discusses what type
of a תשובה teshuvah constitutes תשובה. teshuvah. But it's not enough to
say I קלאפט על חטא klopped al chet on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. It has to be practical things that we see, sorry, does
somebody want to pick up a coffee for...
okay, so you put it there, I'll have reset. Anyway, so the
גמרא, Gemara, it has to be practical things that we see as
a community that they have sort of like done תשובה teshuvah to
change their ways, you know, that allow us to restore our confidence
in them. So that gets discussed in גמרא Gemara in מסכת סנהדרין,
Masechet Sanhedrin, yes.
So you're saying that like, someone could be an עד ed for
a גט? get? Right. And then two years later... so it has
personal status issue, we
take a bit more seriously. Right, like, then two years later they
were found out to be... they signed on a גט get here,
two years later, you know, why not? These are people that had
been cross-examined in court, the court accepted them, presumably the best people
to use for your גט, get, right? Now we find out that
the best people to use for your גט get are people that
never testified in court because anybody who testified in court might turn
out to be עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. So they testified for a
גט get here, two years later they turn, they become עדים זוממים,
edim zomemim, and then the גט get is invalid. Right.
That's right, it's disastrous. Right. Now hopefully the reality is is that
עדים זוממים edim zomemim you assume that it's if you're going to
get הזמים, hazamim, they're going to come soon after, you know, during
this process. It's not going to be two years later somebody, but
you never know. I mean, I know it's disastrous. So I don't
know what to say. That's what רבא's Rava saying. And even רבא
Rava only helps for monetary documents, not for personal status documents.
וזוממים zomemim you're just used for anything.
Right, exactly. Yep. Okay, so we פוסקין pasken like אביי, Abaye, we
have to whatever the consequences are. But it's yeah, it's like it's,
you know, mind-boggling to consider that. So now we continue to the
two dots about five lines from the top. Okay, תנן. Tnan. Now
we're going to look at a little bit about how this plays
out about the מחלוקת אביי ורבא. machloket Abaye ve-Rava. Okay, גנב על
פי שנים, ganav al pi shenayim, let's go back to our משנה.
mishna.
Somebody burgled based on two witnesses, וטבח ומכר על פיהן, ve-tavach u-machar
al pihen, the same two witnesses said that he slaughtered it or
sold it, ונמצאו זוממים, ve-nimtzu zomemim, and they were proven to be
עדים זוממים edim zomemim on the whole shebang. משלמים את הכל, meshalmim
et hakol, they pay everything, they pay four and five. מה לאו
שאילו גניבה וחזר ואילו טביחה? ma lav she-ilu gneva ve-chazar ve-ilu tvicha?
Presumably first they testified that the guy... that he burgled it, and
then they testified he slaughtered and he sold it. Obviously you won't
come to a בית דין Beit Din and say I want to
bring testimony that so and so sold his animal. Right? So first
you testify that he
burgled it and then you testify that he... that he slaughtered it.
Okay. והוזם על הגניבה וחזר והוזם על הטביחה? ve-huzam al hagneva ve-chazar
ve-huzam al hatvicha? And also presumably, although we can debate this, when
they were found to be זוממים, zomemim, people say, oh no no
no, you were with us at that time, so you say that
he burgled it on Monday and slaughtered it on Tuesday. Then other
עדים edim came and they said, you can't say that, you were
with us. Okay. So the first they say, you can't say your
Monday testimony, you were with us on Monday. And then maybe they
come later or they afterwards they say, and you can't say your
Tuesday testimony cause you were with us on Tuesday. You know, what
you said you saw on Tuesday. Okay. והוזמו על אגנבה וחזרו והוזמו
על אטביחה. ve-huzmu al a-gneivah ve-hazru ve-huzmu al a-tvichah. All right. So
where is this all going? ואי סלקא דעתך למפרע הוא נפסל? ve-i
salka daitach le-mafreia hu nifsal? But wait a minute! If אביי Abaye
is right, that they became invalid from the time that they testified
falsely, הני כיון דאיתזמו להו אגנבה? hani keivan de-it-zamu le-hu a-gneivah? Once
they were proven to be עדים זוממים edim zomemim for the גנבה,
gneivah, right?
איגלאי מילתא, iglai milta, we—it now becomes
clear למפרע le-mafreia that כי אסהידו אטביחה, ki ashidu a-tvichah, פסולין הוו,
psulin havu, that they were
פסול. pasul. אמאי? amai? So אמאי משלמי אטביחה? amai m'shalmi a-tvichah? Why
do they pay אטביחה a-tvichah for the slaughtering? So here's the point.
Like, let's say you're on March first, okay, and at, you know,
they supposedly said he was גנב. ganav. What? Yeah, that was at
12:00. Okay. And then at
12:05, they said טבח. tabach. Okay, 12:05. Now, that's what they testified
in court. Then over here, they said, oh, no, no, and he
was גנב ganav on Sunday and טבח tabach on Monday. Okay, that's
what they say. Okay. And they said, oh, wait, wait, you can't
say that you were there and you saw the גנבה gneivah on
Sunday. You were with us on Sunday. Okay, that's what they say
here. Okay, that makes that invalid. Oh, and you can't say that
you saw the טביחה tvichah on Monday. You were with us on
Monday. That makes that invalid. So now the גמרא Gemara is saying,
when did they become פסולי עדים? psulei edim? According to אביי, Abaye,
when did they become פסולי עדים? psulei edim? Now, we say, way
back here, that was their first act of עדות שקר. edut sheker.
They became פסולי עדים psulei edim back here. So if at 12:00,
we now find out that they were עדי שקר, edei sheker, when
they at 12:05 testified about the טביחה, tvichah, we now find out
that they actually were פסולי עדים psulei edim at the time. So
now they're not going to be able to become זוממים zomemim on
this, because it's like you found out that they were relatives or
something. We now see that this not was a false testimony but
was an invalid testimony because now we see that at 12:05 they
were already עדים פסולים. edim psulim. So how are you going to
make them pay for זוממים zomemim for this false testimony if, based
on אביי, Abaye, at that stage they were already עדים פסולים? edim
psulim? Okay, that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Everybody got it?
They should only pay כפל.
kefel. They should pay כפל, kefel, but they shouldn't pay four and
five because by the time they testified four and five, we now
see that they were עדים פסולים. edim psulim. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמאי משלמי אטביחה? amai m'shalmi a-tvichah? Why should they pay
for the testimony about the slaughtering? אמרי הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהוזמו
על הטביחה תחילה. amri hacha be-mai askinan k'gon she-huzmu al ha-tvichah techila.
Okay. Okay, so the case would be that when they said, you
can't say that you were with us, they said the first thing
they said is you were with us on Monday. They first invalidated
this one. But the גמרא's Gemara going to say, but who cares
whether they—what they did first? Okay, at the end of the day,
we're going to invalidate this one, too. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמרי סוף סוף תדיא? amri sof sof tadia? By the end of
the day,
by the time these guys get around to saying you can't—you can't
say that you were there on Sunday, you were with us on
Sunday, so איגלאי מילתא, iglai milta, we now see retroactively דכי אסהידו
אטביחה פסולים הוו. de-ki ashidu a-tvichah psulim havu. אמאי משלמי אטביחה? amai
m'shalmi a-tvichah? So it doesn't matter when they, you know, came to
court and what order they did it in. At the end of
the day, we're going to find out that this was false and
this was false. So if this was false and they became פסולים
psulim here, then this testimony
should never have been accepted in court. And it was not false
testimony; it was invalid testimony. So why are they ever going to
have to pay? It's pretty brilliant, like you never would have thought
to do that, to figure out that math. Okay. Yeah, the answer's
obvious. What's the obvious answer?
They testified at once! Who says 12:00 on Sunday and Monday? And
then something happened also, like, you know, like at once. But everything
happened at once!
All right. So that's obvious to you, but—and you probably learned this
before anyway. So you all know—all right. So the גמרא Gemara says,
anyway, I'm not sure it's so obvious, but—but that is what the
גמרא Gemara says. והלכתא, ve-hilcheta, the way to explain it is, שהעידו
בבת אחת והוזמו. she-eidu b'vat achat ve-huzmu. Okay. So the way is—is
that they said it all at 12:00.
גנב וטבח. ganav ve-tabach. Okay, they could have said at 12:00 גנב
ganav on Sunday—because it takes time to process testimony! Things take a
few minutes. Okay. So here they said...
It makes more sense
at least that הווה אמינא hava amina was that they came in
one day and said that we saw so-and-so steal it, and then
they came in two days later and said and he slaughtered
it.
Yeah, but what I was saying is even if they—right, well, that's
a—right, no,
because—but right, I was just saying even if they all did the
same thing at court, it takes a few minutes. Wait a minute,
you saw it at what day, what was he
wearing, you go a little cross-examining, now let's talk about your other
testimony. I don't think even if they all came in... into court
at the same day that it's obvious that they would say the
whole thing, you know, within one minute. Okay, and actually we're going
to talk about not just one minute, תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei
dibbur. Okay. So they said גנב ganav on Sunday and טבח tavach
on Monday and they did this all at 12:00. Okay, so then
when you retroactively say you were פסולים, psulim, okay, yes, you're פסולים,
psulim, but even אביי Abaye says you never say oh, now we
see we're פסול pasul back then so you can't be an עד
זומם ed zomem because you were פסול pasul when you were testifying.
Like obviously the פסול, psul, the lying as that makes you פסול
pasul is not going to for that same act invalidate the testimony.
It only invalidates you moving forward. Okay, so there's all one testimony
and that's how they can pay four and five. Yes.
If it's תוך כדי- toch k'dei so you're saying when it's תוך
כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur it's בה בת אחת? bah bat achat?
Even if like the שחיטה sh'chita or like he started it and
then he finished it but there's like a five seconds gap between?
Right, right, so the basic- right, point is that it's considered to
be one testimony. Now תוספות Tosafot says the reason בה בת אחת
bah bat achat is considered to be one testimony, this will be
a little bit relevant in a few minutes, is because one of
the implications of- not בה בת אחת, bah bat achat, excuse me,
of תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, is is that you can
retract your statement תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. Like, you know,
you can do this in court, you can do this like you're
making a ברכה, bracha, you know, ברוך אתה ה' אלהינו מלך העולם
שהכל נהיה בדברו Baruch atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam shehakol nihiya bidvaro
על פירות הנפש- al perot hanefash- you know, בורא פרי העץ. borei
peri ha'etz. Right, so if you sort of correct yourself תוך כדי
דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, you can still correct and, you know, amend
your statement.
So what? ויאמר? V'omer? ויאמר, V'omer, right. So anyway, what do you
mean? Like if you say בעומר לעומר? ba'omer la'omer? No, חמישה וארבעים
יום.
chamisha v'arba'im yom.
Right, okay. So anyway, so, so,
so therefore since you can still like correct your original statement, you
know, it's all part of the same testimony because you could have
even gone back and retracted it. So anyway, so that's- it's all
seen as one testimony. So therefore it's not two stages, and when
you're made עד זומם ed zomem for that thing that was all
said in a few seconds of one another, then it's all- then,
you know, then it's all- you're an עד זומם ed zomem on
everything. It's not like you were פסול pasul and then you said
something else.
Just tell me if what you're saying is, let's say two guys
come in, you know, and and their עדות edut is accepted and
processed and then they're proven to be עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, but
then later on it, you know, turns out that they were קרובים
krovim
and then they get off of עד זומם. ed zomem. Or גזלנים.
gazlanim. Right. Okay.
Wouldn't they be פסול, pasul, would they? Mean like as individuals for
anything even though I mean...
That's an interesting question. Meaning the fact that we know that they
were made עדות שקר edut sheker even as- as קרובים, krovim, would
that be enough to make them פסולים מכאן ולהבא. psulim mikan u'l'haba.
They wouldn't be חייב chayav for- for הזמה, hazama, but they might
be חייב chayav just because we now know that
they- but they weren't technically made עדות שקר edut sheker because it
wasn't עדות. edut. It's an interesting question. It's a really good question,
I don't know the answer. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, דהיכא שהעידו בה בת
אחת והוזמו. deheicha she'eidu bah bat achat v'huzmu. לימא כתנאי, Leima kitanna'ei,
let's say this debate between אביי Abaye and רבא Rava is a
debate of תנאים. tanna'im.
היו שנים מעידים אותו שגנב, Hayu shnayim mei'idim oto sheganav, two people
testified that somebody broke- burgled, והן מעידים אותו שטבח, v'hein mei'idim oto
shetavach, witnesses said that he slaughtered,
והוזמו על הגניבה, v'huzmu al hagneiva, and they were found זומם zomem
on the גניבה, gneiva, they weren't found זומם zomem on the טביחה.
tvi'acha.
עדות שבטלה מקצתה בטלה כולה. Eidut shebatla miktzata batla kula. So nobody
pays anything, right? I mean, not nobody pays anything, excuse me. The
עדים זוממים edim zomemim pay כפל, kefel, they were trying to have
him pay for the כפל, kefel, but nobody pays for the four
and the five, right? Because he doesn't pay because if he wasn't
a גנב, ganav, you can't prove he wasn't a גנב, ganav, you
can't prove he's חייב chayav for slaughtering. They don't pay because they
weren't found זוממים zomemim on the טביחה. tvi'acha. Okay, so when you
throw out the גניבה gneiva piece of the testimony, the טביחה tvi'acha
part of the testimony becomes meaningless. All right.
עדות שבטלה
מקצתה בטלה כולה. Eidut shebatla miktzata batla kula. הוזמו
על הטביחה, Huzmu al hatvi'acha, now let's say that they were just
found זוממים zomemim on the טביחה, tvi'acha, not on the original testimony
of the גניבה. gneiva. So he was a גנב ganav but he
wasn't a טובח ומוכר, tove'ach u'mocher, okay, so because they've only been
proven זומם zomem on the טביחה. tvi'acha. So
הוזמו על הטביחה, Huzmu al hatvi'acha, הוא משלם תשלומי כפל, hu m'shalem
tashlumei kefel, the גנב ganav pays כפל, kefel, והן משלמים תשלומי שלשה
v'hein m'shalmim tashlumei shlosha to the גנב, ganav, because now they were
trying to make him pay extra. He was only a גנב, ganav,
he wasn't a טובח ומוכר, tove'ach u'mocher, they were זוממים zomemim on
the טביחה ומכירה. tvi'acha u'mchira. All right, that all makes a lot
of sense. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, says רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yosi, במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when is this true? בשתי
עדויות, Bishtei eiduyot, if the original עדים edim gave two distinct testimonies.
Okay, which we'll discuss in a minute what that means. אבל בעדות
אחת, Aval be'eidut achat, if they all gave one testimony, presumably they
said גנב וטבח ומכר, ganav v'tavach v'machar, right, it was all one
big testimony, עדות שבטלה מקצתה בטלה כולה. eidut shebatla miktzata batla kula.
Then if part is בטל batel the whole is בטל. batel. Now
what does he mean? We already said if you throw out the
גניבה gneiva you throw out the טביחה. tvi'acha. So what he means
is the reverse. If you throw out the טביחה, tvi'acha, you're going
to throw out the גניבה. gneiva. Okay, which is like a little
funny, like what? Just because they were like lying on the טביחה,
tvi'acha, they had actually said the גניבה gneiva thing, they weren't פסולים,
psulim, the פסול psul at any פסול psul happened- first they say
גנב, ganav, and then they said טבח. tavach. So any even if
they were lying on the טביחה tvi'acha that happened afterwards in time,
that's when they became פסולים. psulim. How does that invalidate when they
said גנב? ganav? said גנב. ganav. But presumably what he's saying is
you could go this two ways. You could say we view it
all as like the same time and we say that they were
פסולים psulim at the same moment, so that's even going back a
few seconds, the same way it could go forward a few seconds.
Or his language really is not so much about what do you
call it, about invalidating the people as throwing out the testimony. If
you see this testimony as one unit and you're going to throw
part of it out, you're going to throw all of it out,
okay? You might be familiar with this in other places, you know
there are questions about פלגינן דדיבורא, palginan de-dibura, פגינן? paginan? No, פלגינן.
palginan. פלגינן דדיבורא. palginan de-dibura. Do you take half of what somebody
said, or do you say בטל מקצתו בטל כולו, batel miktsato batel
kulo, if part of it is false, you throw the whole thing
out? So this... Rabbi Yose is less focusing on the people are
פסול psul and he's saying if גניבה gneivah וטביחה tveichah ומכירה u-mechirah
is one package, and you're going to throw out the טביחה tveichah
part because they're זוממים zomemim on the טביחה, tveichah, you're going to
throw the whole thing out. Okay. So let's take a look at
what... what does this have to do with למפרע lemafrea or not?
Well, clearly Rabbi Yose seems to be holding למפרע, lemafrea, because Rabbi
Yose can only sort of say that. Well, let's take a look
at what the גמרא gemara says. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says
like this. מאי בשתי עדויות ומאי בעדות אחת? Mai b-sh'tei eduyot u-mai
b-edut achas?
What do we mean two testimonies and what do we mean one?
אילימא בשתי עדויות בשתי עדויות ממש, Ilima b-sh'tei eduyot b-sh'tei eduyot mamash,
really two separate testimonies. בשתי כיתות, B-sh'tei kitot, meaning it's two separate
groups of witnesses come to testify. Group A says גנב ganav and
Group B says טבח ומכר. tavach u-machar. And there he says when
you throw out the טביחה, tveichah, you won't throw out the גניבה.
gneivah. Okay, but that's שתי עדויות. sh'tei eduyot. And what is בעדות
אחת? b-edut achas? בבת אחת? B-vas achas? בזה אחר זה? Ba-zeh achar
zeh?
So maybe עדות אחת edut achas means one group, group A, but
at separate times: at 12 o'clock and then at 1 o'clock. So
wait a minute. If that's what עדות אחת edut achas means, and
there at 12 o'clock they say גנב ganav and at 1 o'clock
they say טבח ומכר, tavach u-machar, how because they were lying with
the טבח ומכר, tavach u-machar, can you throw out what they said
an hour ago? So the גמרא gemara says, ואמר רבי יוסי בעדות
אחת בבת אחת בזה אחר זה כי משדי, ve-amar Rabbi Yose b-edut
achas b-vas achas ba-zeh achar zeh ki mishaddi, so he would say
with one testimony, one group, one testimony after the other. כי מסהדי
אגניבה, Ki mas'hadi a-gneivah, first they testify at 12 o'clock on the
גניבה. gneivah. והדר מסהדי אטביחה, Ve-hadar mas'hadi a-tveichah, and at 1 o'clock
they testify on the slaughtering. כי מזממי אטביחה, Ki mizzammemi a-tveichah, when
they're found זוממים zomemim on the slaughtering, עדות שבטלה מקצתה בטלה כולה?
edut she-batlah miktsatah batlah kullah? You're going to throw the whole thing
out? ואיזממו אגניבה? Ve-itzmumu a-gneivah? They'll be זוממים? zomemim? It doesn't literally
mean זוממים, zomemim, but they'll be invalid or the testimony will be
invalid when they testified about the גניבה? gneivah? מהיכא תיתי הך? Me-heicha
teisi hach? Where do you get that from? Okay, so that's a
great... by the way, talk about like good idioms from the גמרא,
gemara, like מהיכא תיתי, me-heicha teisi, where did this come from? Like,
you know, where would you get that from? Okay, so where would
this idea come from? Right? How could because they were found זוממים
zomemim at 1 o'clock you throw out for you know something that
they testified on an hour ago? אלא לאו, Ela lav, what he
must mean is when is it that you don't package it all
together, שתי עדויות sh'tei eduyot you consider it separate testimonies, בעדות אחת
כעין שתי עדויות. b-edut achas k-ein sh'tei eduyot. It means two testimonies...
it means it's actually one testimony that's like two. ומאי נינהו? U-mai
ninhu? What's one testimony like two? בזה אחר זה, Ba-zeh achar zeh,
one group, first they did one and then an hour later they
did the other or even 10 minutes later they did the other.
אבל בעדות אחת בבת אחת, Aval b-edut achas b-vas achas,
so what does he mean when he says it's one testimony? It
means that it's all at the same time, it's like תוך כדי
דיבור. tokh k-dei dibbur. לא, Lo, then you would say that... then
you would say that if it's all one group testifying at the
same time like תוך כדי דיבור, tokh k-dei dibbur, even if you
throw out the second half of their testimony, you gotta throw the
whole thing out. Alright, so what... why do the רבנן rabbanan argue
on that? That makes a lot of sense, you'd view it all
as one package. So the גמרא gemara says, וסברו נא, ve-savru na,
now we're going to assume... I'm sorry, וסברו נא, ve-savru na, now
we are assuming דכולי עלמא תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי. de-khulei alma
tokh k-dei dibbur k-dibbur dami. Everybody, both Rabbi Yose and the רבנן
rabbanan would hold of the principle of תוך כדי דיבור. tokh k-dei
dibbur. Okay, that makes sense, right? That's a pretty generally assumed principle.
Everybody agrees that that defines things as being in one unit taking
place in one moment in time. Okay. So therefore so why do
the רבנן rabbanan argue? If it's all תוך כדי דיבור tokh k-dei
dibbur testimony and you threw out the טביחה, tveichah, you should throw
out everything, you should throw out the גניבה. gneivah. So מאי לאו
הא בה קא מיפלגי? mai lav ha beh ka mipalgi? This must
be what is debated about. דרבנן סברי מכאן ולהבא הוא ניפסל, de-rabbanan
סברי mikan u-le-haba hu nifsul, the Rabbis say like Rava, it's only
from this point onwards he's disqualified. וכיון דמהאי שעתא קא מזממי אטביחה
קא מזממי, ve-kivan d-me-hai sha'ata ka mizzammemi a-tveichah ka mizzammemi, and since
it's only from this point onwards that they are defined as זוממים
zomemim and the testimony is defined as invalid, אטביחה דקא מזממי איזממו
a-tveichah de-ka mizzammemi itzomemu for the slaughtering that they've been found זוממים
zomemim they're זוממים. zomemim. אגניבה דלא מזממי לא איזממו, a-gneivah de-lo mizzammemi
lo itzomemu, but for the גניבה, gneivah, they're not considered זוממים. zomemim.
So what does that mean? They said here in one time: גנב
וטבח ומכר. ganav ve-tavach u-machar. These עדים זוממים eidim zomemim months later
said, "No, no, no, I'm sorry buddy, you weren't... the טביחה tveichah
is a lie." Okay, everybody with me? So Rabbi Yose says it's
all one package. This is one עדות, edut, you threw away part
of it, throw the whole thing out. That's according to Abaye. But
according to Rava, Rava actually says, "No, no, no, for the next...
for the last five months this actually they were כשר kasher witnesses,
and..." And and maybe like the testimony was כשר *kosher* testimony. But
we're saying starting at December 1st, right, at starting December 1st, we're
saying the צביחה *tzvichah* for this entire time, okay, they were כשר
*kosher* and גנב וטבח *ganav utvach* was an acceptable was a כשר
*kosher* testimony. Starting on December 1st, the צביחה *tzvichah* gets thrown out
of court. Okay, that's the principle like אין לך אלא משעת חידושו
ואילך *ein lacha ela mishas chiddusho va'eilach*. And starting at this point
in time, they become פסול pasul, *pasul* witnesses. Okay, so fine, so
how would we throw out the whole package? Back here they were
כשר *kosher*, back here the whole testimony was accepted as a package.
We're only going to throw this out a long time
later, okay, so it's no longer like one package, you know, to
throw out. All right? So so that would be what the חכמים
Chachamim. *chachamim* would say, and רב rav יוסי *Rav Yosi* would say
no, no, no, you go back here and at this moment they
become פסול pasul. *pasul*, the עדות eidus, *eidus* becomes פסול pasul *pasul*,
the עדות *eidus* is never good, you throw the whole thing out.
Okay, רב rav יוסי *Rav Yosi*
so and רב יוסי סבר למפרע נפסל *Rav Yosi savar lemafrei nifsal*.
No, it's retroactive. וכיון דמדי דאסהידו הוא דמיפסלי *vekeivan demidi de'ashidu hu
demipsali*, as soon as they testified they're פסול *pasul*. Now again, I've
been trying to talk about throwing out the עדות *eidus* because I've
been trying to be accurate with what רב יוסי *Rav Yosi* says.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be focusing on invalidating the witnesses,
okay? So רב יוסי *Rav Yosi* says from this moment they're invalid
and therefore you throw out the testimony, right, and therefore so because
it's retroactive. Whereas if you said מכאן ולהבא mikan ule-haba, *mikan u'lehaba*,
you only invalidated them here, so of course the testimony of גניבה
gneiva. *gneiva* remains good, they only became invalid here. But the גניבה
*gneiva* testimony never got thrown out. Okay, but רב יוסי סבר למפרע
נפסל *Rav Yosi savar lemafrei nifsal*, וכיון דמדי דאסהידו הוא דמיפסלי *vekeivan
demidi de'ashidu hu demipsali*, as soon as they testified they became invalid.
כי איתזממו אטביחה *ki itzmuluhu a'tavichah*, when they became
invalid witnesses because of the testimony of the of the slaughtering, איתזממו
נמי אגניבה *itzmuluhu nami a'gneiva*, they also became invalid for the testimony
of the גניבה *gneiva*. דתוכ כדיבור כדיבור דמי *de'toch k'deibor k'deibor dami*,
because everybody presumably holds תוכ כדיבור כדיבור דמי *toch k'deibor k'deibor dami*.
So look, this debate is the debate of אביי Abaye ורבא *Abaye
v'Rava*. רב יוסי *Rav Yosi* clearly holds, רב יוסי *Rav Yosi* is
clearly אביי Abaye *Abaye*. רב יוסי *Rav Yosi* clearly holds you go
back retroactively, you look at that time, you say that the טביחה
tvicha, *tavichah* was no good, so you throw out the whole עדות
*eidus*, so you throw out the whole עדים edim *eidin* from that
point onwards which includes the point of the גניבה *gneiva* which happened
a few seconds earlier. רב יוסי *Rav Yosi* is clearly אביי Abaye
*Abaye*, retroactive. The question is what do the חכמים *chachamim* hold? So
we're saying the חכמים *chachamim* hold like רבא Rava, *Rava*, מכאן ולהבא
*mikan u'lehaba*. So since back then they were כשר *kosher* and they've
been כשר *kosher* for the last few months, you're not going to
throw out the גניבה *gneiva* part of the testimony. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
no,
because we're going to since we פסקן *pasken* like אביי *Abaye*, we're
going to sort of say that everybody here now goes according to
אביי *Abaye*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אמרי Amrei,
לא *amri lo*, אי תוכ כדיבור כדיבור דמי *ei toch k'deibor k'deibor
dami*, if everybody were to agree that תוכ כדיבור כדיבור דמי *toch
k'deibor k'deibor dami*, דכולי עלמא למפרע נפסל *de'kulei alma lemafrei nifsal*, everybody
would say retroactive, meaning everybody holds like אביי *Abaye*, it is retroactive,
okay? And if everybody were to say תוכ כדיבור *toch k'deibor*, everybody
would agree you throw out the whole testimony, even the גניבה *gneiva*
part that came before because it was all one unit. Okay? אלא
הכא בתוכ כדיבור כדיבור דמי קמיפלגי *ela hacha b'toch k'deibor k'deibor dami
kamifligi*. The debate is, do you hold of the principle of תוכ
כדיבור כדיבור דמי *toch k'deibor k'deibor dami*? Do you hold that something
that is maybe if it were you would now again, there's degrees,
like maybe you could hold of תוכ כדיבור *toch k'deibor* that I
can correct a statement that I just said, but maybe something that's
conceptually distinct? Like if I'm going to say גנב *ganav* and then
I'm going to say טבח ומכר *tavach umachar*, so conceptually טבח ומכר
*tavach umachar* is a separate testimony from the גנב *ganav*, we're not
going to use תוכ כדיבור *toch k'deibor* to turn it into one
testimony. Okay, so there's always a question: when you deny תוכ כדיבור
*toch k'deibor*, what do you mean? Like how does the first my
first word in my sentence be the same testimony as the last
word in my sentence? You know, there's got to be a certain
time where you define something as one unit. But if it's conceptually
two units, the fact that it's תוכ כדיבור *toch k'deibor* is not
going to make it all one. So the רבנן *rabanan* would say
even if this is
12:01:00 and this is 12:00:10,
whatever, that's 10 seconds later, those are two separate testimonies. And therefore
just because you threw out this part, they only became פסול *pasul*
from 12 o'clock and 10 seconds. And the testimony of 12 o'clock
and 10 seconds is a distinct testimony, and what they testified before
remains valid. So everybody agrees it's retroactive, the question is if it
was said תוכ כדיבור *toch k'deibor* does it force it all to
be seen of as one moment in time and one testimony? Let
me just turn the part. אלא הכא בתוכ כדיבור כדיבור דמי קמיפלגי
*ela hacha b'toch k'deibor k'deibor dami kamifligi*. רבנן סברי תוכ כדיבור לאו
כדיבור דמי *rabanan savri toch k'deibor lav k'deibor dami*, we don't treat
it as all one statement. ורב יוסי סבר תוכ כדיבור כדיבור דמי
*ve'Rav Yosi savar toch k'deibor k'deibor dami*. And he says no, it
is one statement and if you throw out part of it, even
the second part, you're going to throw the whole part out. Okay,
there's a
question—no, that was—what you're
saying is that you can separate two parts of the sentence and
say the person's guilty for this part and not for that part?
Correct.
Well, certainly the second part. You can throw out the second part
without throwing out the first part.
And the other person's saying you can't separate?
Exactly, exactly, yeah. Meaning that's what I said before, like it's is
it all just about the amount of time? Like certainly everybody would
agree that if I have one topic to testify about and it
takes me five minutes to describe what I'm talking about, we don't
say each one of those is a separate testimony, right? So how
there should be other contextual factors or factors that determine whether to
package it all as one unit or not. I agree with to
some degree we're going to see that now, but the גמרא Gemara
is not getting into that yet.
Do they have like cases? There were charges that were
brought or I'm trying to see.
Yeah, it's true like you could have a case like the גמרא
Gemara often discusses like I bring you to court and I bring
the witnesses like which is how you would imagine it, but you
could also have a case where witnesses just come and say we
come up and knock on the court and say we saw something,
we're good citizens reporting on something that we saw. Right, you don't
technically everything you don't need a litigant. I think that's even true
in civil court, not in civil, in criminal court when it's a
crime against a person, right, even though technically the state doesn't need
somebody to press charges, right, they're not going to bother to pursue
it on most cases unless the victim is pressing charges, right? But
but yeah, in a civil court you definitely need a litigant, but
in these cases in theory the witnesses could just show up on
their own. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. וסבר
רבי יוסי תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי? V'savar Rabbi Yosei toch k'dei
dibbur k'dibbur dami? Whoa,
one minute, now this is really going to be a question however
you explain the position of the חכמים. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei clearly
says it's all one package and if you throw out the טביחה,
tevicha you throw out the גניבה. But one minute, does he really
hold תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי? toch k'dei dibbur k'dibbur dami? Why
not?
והתנן ותנן במשנה, V'hatnan utnan bemishnah, somebody says הרי זו תמורת עולה
תמורת שלמים. harei zo tmuras olah tmuras shelamim. הרי זו תמורת עולה
דברי רבי מאיר. harei zo tmuras olah divrei Rabbi Meir. So people
remember what a תמורה tmura is? תמורה tmura is you have an
animal that's קדוש kadosh and you say now if that animal gets
a מום mum and a blemish, you can redeem it on money,
but if it doesn't have a מום, mum, you can't redeem it
and even if it does have a מום, mum, you can't go
ahead and try to transfer the קדושה kedusha from animal one straight
to animal two. That's called a תמורה, tmura, an exchange, and the
תורה Torah says if you try to exchange, והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה
קדש. v'hayah hu u'tmurato yihyeh kodesh. So what you tried to sanctify
is sanctified, but the animal itself retains its original sanctity. So let's
say you had a עולה olah and a שלמים shelamim here in
front of you, okay, and you took this other animal, this third
animal, and you said this animal is a תמורת תמורת עולה תמורת
שלמים. tmuras tmuras olah tmuras shelamim. Okay, so what were you trying
to do?
Were you trying to transfer the עולה קדושה, olah kedusha, the שלמים
קדושה, shelamim kedusha, were you correcting yourself, were you trying to do
both? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you go by the first
part of your statement. You said תמורת עולה, tmuras olah, that took
effect,
the animal has the קדושה kedusha of an עולה. olah. First one
remains as it was. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יוסי
אומר אם לכך נתכוון מתחלה, Rabbi Yosei omer im l'kach nitkaven mitechilah,
if, and here gets the question of intent or context, if you
were intending from the very outset to make this animal both an
עולה olah and a שלמים, shelamim, okay, you thought you could make
it half and half, so הואיל ואי אפשר להוציא שני שמות כאחת.
ho'il v'ee efshar l'hotzi shnei sheimos k'achas. Now you can't get both
words out of your mouth at the same time. One of those
two words has to come first. Okay? So therefore we don't say
we're going to force the first half of your sentence. Clearly you
were trying to say both and you had to get the words
out in a particular order. So in that case, דבריו קיימים, devarav
kayyamim, we'll accept the whole sentence. Now it sounds like we ask
you what were you intending, right, which is interesting like when do
we go by your claim of what you thought. תוספות Tosafot tries
to say he doesn't, תוספות Tosafot questions this, he says it would
be דברים שבלב, devarim she'bleiv, maybe we use other evidence to indicate
what you were intending or whatever. But anyway, let's just go with
what he said. He says if we know somehow that that's what
you were trying to say, then we don't chop the sentence in
half. That was one statement and it all applies, and the animal
is half each. What do you do with an animal that's half
each? So you wait till it gets a מום, mum, a blemish,
and you transfer half of its value to money that's going to
be used for an עולה olah and the other half of its
value to money that's going to be used for a שלמים. shelamim.
Okay, but you've succeeded in making it half each. Okay, דבריו קיימים.
devarav kayyamim. ואם אמר תמורת עולה ונמלך ואמר תמורת שלמים, V'im amar
tmuras olah v'nimlach v'amar tmuras shelamim, if however you changed your mind,
you said תמורת עולה, tmuras olah, ah, תמורת שלמים, tmuras shelamim, right,
it was clear you were trying to correct yourself, so in that
case, הרי זו תמורת עולה, harei zo tmuras olah, then you're stuck,
it's a תמורת עולה, tmuras olah, which is basically a principle that
you don't say תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur even to amend
your statement, let alone when you're saying something else. Now there could
still be a difference between amending your statement and continuing your statement.
You're in court and you're spending five minutes describing what occurred, that's
one testimony, that's all a continuation of your statement. But a correction
of your statement, something new to revise or whatever, I'm sorry, once
you said it you're stuck by it. Now you could also say
is it the same? You know, maybe when you sanctify something, you
know, this set's all about speech and the power of speech to
create metaphysical realities as it were, maybe that happens immediately, maybe court
is always more about a process. It is about speech, but it's
about a process,
cross-examination. etcetera, etcetera. So maybe by court there's different rules. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara here, as it often does, assumes until it's going
to be forced, until it's forced to say otherwise, that it's going
to be all the same rules across the board. So here רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi says you don't say תוך כדי דיבור. Toch K'dei
Dibbur. How could he say in our case you throw it all
out? Clearly, he's saying it's all one testimony. Did you want to
say something, Jenna?
I'm just thinking about נדרים Nedarim and what we talk about—I don't
know, we had a similar conversation of where does it matter, the
פה peh and why we were trying to figure out why it's
okay to shift what you were meaning in נדרים Nedarim but not
in other places, and I wonder how that fits in.
You mean like we say an idea of פיו ולבו שוין, piv
velibbo shavin, that what you're thinking has to be consistent with what
you're saying and so on. Right. I mean that's obviously another thing
to say. The opposite argument to this, as it's from the power
of speech argument, is that by things that are הפלאה, hafla'ah, speech
acts or whatever that create these metaphysical changes, it's critical that your
speech is in sync with what you're thinking. And here you're basically
saying, "No, I actually accidentally said the wrong thing," right? So if
I could do like a התרת נדרים Hatarat Nedarim to say that
I hadn't intended—here you clearly, the wrong words came out of your
mouth. So, yeah, those are all really good questions. Okay, so but
let's see how the גמרא Gemara resolves it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so here רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi doesn't seem to care about
the fact that you corrected yourself, and here he seems to consider
one testimony. You could make other distinctions. You could say you're not
allowed to correct yourself, no, you can't give emendations, but if you
but anything you say within תוך כדי דיבור Toch K'dei Dibbur is
all considered part of one whole, right? There's so many different ways
you could distinguish between why here it's one testimony and there you
can't correct yourself. But the גמרא Gemara gives what I consider to
be a very technical and boring way of distinguishing between the two.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, ואבינן בה, ve-aveinan
bah, so we asked on this. דימלך פיתיה, dimlach peitya,
if you changed your mind, meaning at a later time, of course
you're stuck with what you first said. ואמר רב פפא, ve-amar Rav
Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa says, no, here's the חידוש. chiddush.
The חידוש chiddush is נמלך בתוך כדי דיבור קאמרינן. nimlach betoch k'dei
dibbur kaamrinan. Even if you corrected yourself within כדי דיבור, k'dei dibbur,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would say you can't amend your statement and
it's still a תמורת עולה. tmurat olah. So there he doesn't hold
of תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, you can't amend it, and
here he holds that if it's תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur,
it's
one unit. So a million ways to distinguish the two cases. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמרי, no, here's how you could
answer it. תרי תוך כדי דיבור הוי. trei toch k'dei dibbur havei.
There are two measures of תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. חד
כדי שאילת תלמיד לרב, chad k'dei she'elat talmid l'rav, one is the
time it takes a תלמיד talmid to ask after the wellbeing of
his רבי, rebbe, which is basically
שלום עליך רבי ומורי. Shalom alecha rabbi u-mori. Okay, that's a long
תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. וחד, ve-chad, and the other one
is כדי שאילת הרב לתלמיד, k'dei she'elat ha-rav l'talmid, when the רב
greets the תלמיד talmid and says שלום עליכם Shalom aleichem or שלום
עליך. Shalom alecha. So it's twice as long, it's a half a
second or a second. Okay, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi holds of
the תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur the half-second, but not of
the second.
Okay, that's got to be the most boring distinction possible. Okay, so
כי לית ליה לרבי יוסי, ki leit lei le-Rabbi Yossi, when does
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi not hold of תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei
dibbur that you can't amend your statement in this case of עולה
olah and שלמים, shlamim,
כדי שאילת תלמיד לרב, k'dei she'elat talmid l'rav, the longer one. If
it took four seconds, I mean four words, one full second. כדי
שאילת תלמיד לרב שלום עליך רבי ומורי. k'dei she'elat talmid l'rav, shalom
alecha rabbi u-mori. כי נפיש, ki nafish, that's long. But כדי שאילת
רב לתלמיד, k'dei she'elat rav l'talmid, but the time it takes a
רב to ask a תלמיד, talmid, שלום עליך, shalom alecha, אית ליה,
it lei, and he would say it's all one package. Okay, so
anyway, a lot more other ways you could have distinguished between a
court case and a קדושה kedusha case, between amending versus appending, all
these types of differences that the גמרא Gemara ignores. But bottom line
here is a fascinating idea that according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
right, if you say למפרע הוא נפסל, lemifraia hu nifsal, even if
you throw out the second part of the statement, if it's all
תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur in one statement, then you throw
out the whole statement. Okay, so that certainly assumes אביי of למפרע
הוא נפסל. lemifraia hu nifsal. By the way, I want to read
one line in תוספות, Tosafot, because it's a famous position of רבנו
תם. Rabbeinu Tam. What is the logic of
תוך כדי דיבור? toch k'dei dibbur? So usually you say because there's
got to be a amount of time that we say defines things
as all taking place within the same
time, either the—so I mean, and the idea, the most radical example
that תוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, like there's different ways you
could sort of say it. You could say that it's dealing with
this very fundamentally, and that's why the דיבור, dibbur, the nature of
the speech act, as we were sort of saying, like speech is
trying to articulate what you're thinking, but like you can't always say
everything in one moment and those aren't, and sometimes you get things
wrong or whatever, so there's like thinking of the speech act as
a certain amount of time that we view to view things as
like one unit, correctable, all one type of speech, as different acts
of speech and so on. Okay, that's so like thinking of תוך
כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur specifically in the context of an act
of speech, and defining it as one unit. or not. But there's
another example of תוך כדי דיבור Toch Kedei Dibur which is an
extreme example, which is somebody hears that his father dies and he
does קריעה. Kriah. And then it turns out like oh actually when
we told you your father died, he hadn't died yet, but he
died a second after you did קריעה. Kriah. Oh, well it was
תוך כדי דיבור Toch Kedei Dibur so the קריעה Kriah counts. Okay.
So that's like the קריעה Kriah occurred before the father died, but
because it was תוך כדי דיבור Toch Kedei Dibur of the death,
it counts. So that seems to be an idea that תוך כדי
דיבור Toch Kedei Dibur is considered to be defining halachically what's considered
the same moment in time. Okay? Like what's a degree of precision
of measuring the same moment in time. Alright, so that's the questions
of תוך כדי דיבור. Toch Kedei Dibur. Either thinking about it as
a speech act type of a thing or thinking about it as
a moment in time. רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam has a very strange,
I mean it's strange because it's like it seems out of nowhere
idea, because he's bothered with why is the measure שלום עליך Shalom
Alecha and שלום עליך רבי ומורי? Shalom Alecha Rabbi u'Mori? Like why
are we using that as the measure? So if you take a
look at תוספות, Tosfos, the תוספות Tosfos כי לית ליה לרבי יוסי,
Ki Leis Lei l'Rabbi Yosi, he says here in the following. It's
one, two, three, four, five, six lines down in the from the
beginning of the wide lines in תוספות, Tosfos, like five words in.
So he says the following. He says,
he says the following. He says מפרש רבנו תם Mefaresh Rabbeinu Tam
דהיינו טעמא, d'hainu taama, this is the reason of תוך כדי דיבור.
Toch Kedei Dibur. דכשאדם
מעיד עדות, d'che'she'adam me'id eidus, if a person is giving testimony, או
עושה מקח וממכר, o oseh mikach u'mimkar, because another kind you can
use תוך כדי דיבור Toch Kedei Dibur is you're buying something and
then you want to back out or change your mind or change
the conditions or whatever, וחברו נותן לו שלום. v'chaveiro nosein lo shalom.
So there you are. Now you can imagine this in the marketplace.
You're trying to do some transaction and somebody comes up, 'Oh Chaim,
how you doing? Like what? I'm trying to buy something here.' So
you have to say, 'Oh hello' and then get back to what
you're doing. Okay, of course it's a little funny, imagine this in
court. I
hereby testify whatever, here's the testimony. 'Hey Abba! How you
doing?' Anyway. So he says או רבו, o rabo, either your friend
or your רבי rebbe gives you a hello, על כרחו יש לו
להשיב ולהפסיק. al korcho yesh lo lehashiv u'lehafsik. You have to stop
your business transaction or your testimony and say hello back. Why?
כדאמר בברכות, kedamar b'Brachos, הנותן שלום לחברו ואינו מחזיר hanosein shalom l'chaveiro
v'eino machazir נקרא גזלן, nikra gazlan, שנאמר גזלת העני בבתיכם. shene'emar gezelas
he'ani b'vateichem. So of course in court you'd better respond to this
if not you're a גזלן gazlan and they'll throw out your testimony.
Anyway, so since sometimes you find yourself in this situation where you
have to respond back, ולכך תקנו חכמים u'le'kach tiknu chachamim שלא יהא
נחשב הפסק. she'lo yehei nchashav hefsek. So the rabbis said we're not
going to consider that an interruption. We allow for that. But he
makes it all like a rabbinic תקנה. takanah. Now it's very funny,
if it's a rabbinic תקנה, takanah, it's like here it has all
these implications for עדות, for like you know for נדר, neder, for
all these things. Like to make this a rabbinic תקנה takanah is
a very strange way of phrasing it. Like again, you could have
said because of those realities
we defined that what means the same period of time of speaking
allows for those types of small interruptions. But the word תקנה takanah
is a funny word. Like you could have said לכך אמרו חכמים,
le'kach amru chachamim, you know that this is all considered to be
the same period of time. But he says this word of תקנה.
takanah. But obviously because it's this type of thing that it's about
talking and being interrupted, he has the problem with the גמרא Gemara.
about the קריעה. Kriah. Okay? Then he says if you skip to
the end of that line, he says ומיהו u'mihu בפרק... what would
it be? וכן מוכח בנזיר דקאמר טוב לשבקתיה רבך לתלמיד, that if
you don't allow for תוך כדי דיבור Toch Kedei Dibur you don't
allow a תלמיד talmid to respond. ומיהו בפרק בתרא דנדרים u'mihu b'Perek
Basra d'Nedarim אין מתיישב טעם זה. ein misyasheiv taam zeh. At the
end of נדרים Nedarim this reason doesn't work. Why? לענין קריעה. le'inyan
kriah. In the case about doing קריעה. Kriah. דקסבר שמת. d'kasavar she'meis.
He thought that his father had died, וקרע ואחר כך מת. v'kara
v'achar kach meis. And then he died afterwards. אם מת תוך כדי
דיבור יצא ידי קריעה, im meis toch kedei dibur yatza yedei kriah,
ואם לאו לא יצא ידי קריעה. v'im lav lo yatza yedei kriah.
So what does that have to do with interrupting your speech and
not considering it an interruption in your speech?
ואולי מה שהשיבו בזה. v'ulai mah she'heshivu b'zeh. Alright, maybe that's only
rabbinic, it's you know the rabbis go easy in אבילות aveilus situations,
so right, but it doesn't really fit. Okay, we have to give
some other explanation for that. But the basic question is I would
like to take out the תקנה takanah part of רבנו תם Rabbeinu
Tam and say the two explanations of תוך כדי דיבור Toch Kedei
Dibur is one is it's defining halachically what means, what does it
mean that something occurred at the same moment in time. And the
other is the question of a speech act, you know, and we
forget this question about like תקנו, tiknu, but the point is we
can't get all of our words out at once, sometimes you know
you know there are moments of interruption and so on, and what
is defined... and you know our thoughts are sometimes we say wrong
things and we need to correct them and what's defined as one
type of a speech act as opposed to two speech acts, right?
That's I think the more you know the more natural way of
saying it. Alright, so back to the גמרא Gemara now. אמר רבא.
Amar Rava. Middle of
ע"ג עמוד ב'. Ayin Gimmel Amud Beis. So now we've dealt with
it works retroactively and if it's תוך כדי דיבור... Toch Kedei Dibur...
you throw the whole testimony out even if the only thing that
was invalidated was the second part of it. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
now says רבא, Rava now remember, this is also this isn't directly
connected to the question of retroactive or מכאן ולהבא, but there are
ways they might intersect. עדים שהוכחשו ולבסוף הוזמו, Edim she-huch-cheshu u-le-vasof huzmu,
witnesses who were first contradicted and then they were made עדים זוממים.
edim zomemim. Okay, so witnesses said
ראובן, Reuven, you know, killed שמעון Shimon on Sunday and other witnesses
said you can't say that ראובן Reuven was with us at a
ball game on Sunday. They don't say you were with us. They
say ראובן Reuven was with us. Okay, or they could say we
were at that spot. What, you said it happened, you know, at
the intersection of whatever, these two streets, we were at that spot
at that time and we didn't see it happen. So it's contradictory
testimony but it's not הזמה, hazama, it's not saying you were with
us. Okay, so in that רבא Rava says let's say first that
happened. Now we said if the עדים edim became פסול, then retroactively
they won't have been then they won't have been עדים זוממים. edim
zomemim. But let's say the עדים edim didn't become פסול. Let's say
first you threw out their testimony because it was contradicted, which doesn't
mean we believe the second group. It just means we can't believe
either group. Okay, so we throw it out. You can even have
a case where we throw it out because we know it's wrong.
They say ראובן Reuven killed שמעון Shimon and then שמעון Shimon walks
into court. I love that case! בהרוג ברגליו. be-harug be-raglav. Okay, so
we know it's false but it's not זוממים. zomemim. And then it's
זוממים. zomemim. Then witnesses come and say, "Oh, you were with us
on that day." Do we say since the testimony has already been
thrown out, okay, you can no longer turn them into עדים זוממים,
edim zomemim, or do we say, you know, it's all part of
the process of of destroying their testimony? So we don't sort of
make that we're not saying they were פסול at the time they
testified, so we're not sort of making, you know, so therefore this
is not contradictory or this doesn't prevent us from continuing on to
make them into עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Okay, so that's what he
says. עדים שהוכחשו ולבסוף הוזמו, Edim she-huch-cheshu u-le-vasof huzmu, so they were
first proven to be false or it was contradicted and then they
were זוממו, zumemu, in a case let's say they testified ראובן Reuven
killed שמעון. Shimon. נהרגין, Neheragin, they could still become עדים זוממים edim
zomemim and be put to death if they were found עדים זוממים
edim zomemim after. דהכחשה תחילת הזמה היא, De-hach-chasha techilat hazama hi, the
process of contradiction is seen as the beginning of a process of
making them עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. I mean, you don't obviously need
to work through that process, but it's all part of the same
process of attacking their testimony. So it's not like, oh, the testimony
has already been contradicted, we can't, you know, you know, there's no
longer we can no longer make it עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, they've
already been thrown out. You don't say that.
What did he say? Yes.
אלא שלא
נגמרה, Ella she-lo nigmira, I'm sorry, yeah, it was the beginning of
a process but hadn't been completed. והזמה ve-hazama is the full completion
of the process, presumably because ignore my example where where ראובן Reuven
walks in the victim walks in alive into court, normally it certainly
makes sense if הכחשה hach-chasha is just we don't know who's telling
the truth. So we don't know who's telling the truth. We didn't
accept your testimony because we have contradictory testimony. Okay, but now the
process of throwing out your testimony has begun but it hasn't ended.
It began because it might be false and we're not going to
use it, but making it זוממים zomemim is like the end of
the process because now we know for certain that it's false, we
know you're lying because we know you're זומם. zomem. I'm sorry, Hillel,
what was your question?
Well, I'm not now I'm not now sure if I'm saying anything
at all, but is it is it saying that הכחשה hach-chasha is
the same thing as הזמה, hazama, except missing it's missing a kind
of finality? Or is it saying that these עדים זוממים edim zomemim
complete what עדים הכחשה edim hach-chasha said?
I don't see it I mean, you're right, the language is saying
those those things, but I see it I'm reading it more more
in a minimalist way and just sort of saying that the process
of הכחשה hach-chasha doesn't prevent us from you know, it's not seen
as like Until now we've been talking about ways that we can't
make you an עד זומם. ed zomem. You're proved to have been
a גזלן. gazlan. You're proved to, you know, we threw out the
טביחה testimony so it undermines this testimony. You were למפרע הוא נפסל,
le-mafrea hu nifsal, etc. And here we're just saying like because these
are all about contradicting the testimony, it doesn't get in the way
of us processing the הזמה hazama case. Okay, but conceptually because תחילת
הזמה techilat hazama meaning, not like it's a necessary part of the
process, it's not like we call it הזמה hazama the you know,
the process is very different, one is saying you were with us
and the other is saying whatever, but just that it's consistent with
like you know, the idea of הזמה hazama that's going to come
afterwards. All right, so the גמרא says like this. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, מנא אמינא לה? Mena amina la? Where do I get this
idea from? דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Beraita. מעידים
אנו באיש פלוני, Maidim anu be-ish ploni, we testify about ראובן, Reuven,
שסימא את עין עבדו והפיל את שינו. she-sima et ein avdo ve-hipil
et shino. He blinded his servant, knocked out the eye and afterwards
knocked out the tooth. Now you realize the servant goes free if
either an eye or a tooth or any limb or whatever is
destroyed. But the question here is going to be what order did
it happen in? So it's better for the slave, I say servant,
slave, it's better for the slave that it should have been first
the tooth and then the eye, because if it's first the tooth,
then he becomes a free man, and then the eye got knocked
out, and then he gets compensated for the loss of the eye,
okay, as if it's the reverse he gets compensated for the loss
of the tooth. Compensated for the loss of the eye is much
bigger than the compensation for the loss of the tooth. Okay, so
they testified, first he blinded his slave and then he knocked out
his tooth. the eye and then he knocked out the tooth. הרי
הרב אומר כן, Harei harav omer kein, the master is happy with
that testimony, at least he's happy with that order. Now the גמרא's
going to say if there was no preceding testimony against him, he
would not be happy with that either. That's going to make him
lose a slave and pay for the tooth. But assuming that the
alternative is the opposite order, he's happy to have them testify this
order.
Okay, ונמצאו זוממין. Venimtzu zomemin. Now they were found זוממין. zomemin. So
again, assuming that for whatever reason, and this is what רבא's Rava
going to use to prove his case, that the backdrop is the
alternative was the opposite order, so then they, in their testimony, help
the owner. They help the owner that they knocked down his payment
from the payment of an eye to the payment of a tooth.
So if they're זוממין, zomemin, who do they have to pay? If
they're זוממין, zomemin, who do they pay? The slave. They pay the
slave the difference between the value of the eye and the value
of the tooth, right? You got it? Because if it was the
other order that had been assumed and they reversed the order, they're
helping the master and hurting the slave, knocking it down to the
value of the tooth. So משלמין דמי עין לעבד, Meshalamin dmei ayin
l'eved, they pay the cost of the eye to the slave minus
the tooth. So okay, that's the פשט pshat of the thing. Now
רבא Rava says, what where do we get the backdrop that the
opposite order was assumed, right? היכי
דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא כדקתני, Ilima k'diktani, like it
is, like they were the first to come into court with these
witnesses, דליכא כת אחרינא, d'leika kat achrina, there's no other witnesses, משלמין
דמי עין לעבד, meshalamin dmei ayin l'eved, they have to pay the
slave for the eye? So before they came, the slave was a
slave, there was no, you know, they were making the master liable.
בתר דאפקי ליה לחירות, Basar d'afkei lei l'cheirus, after they freed him,
דמי עינו קא בעי שלומי, dmei eino ka baei shalumei, and have
to pay him for his eye? Meaning their testimony was helping the
slave if nothing preceded them. They were getting the slave free.
ועוד דהוה ליה עדי הרב לשלומי, Ve'od d'hava lei edi harav l'shalumei,
who were they hurting? If nothing preceded them, they were hurting the
owner. They were saying the owner had to free his slave and
they were lying about it.
ועוד והרי הרב אומר כן, Ve'od vaharei harav omer kein, the master
is happy with their testimony? הרב מי ניחא ליה, Harav mi nicha
lei, he's not happy with their testimony if they're the first people
to show up to court; before then he was going to get
off. אלא לאו, Ela lav, the only way this makes sense, and
obviously this is correct, is there was a backdrop that the opposite
had been assumed. כגון דאתו בי תרי, Kegon d'atu bei trei, two
other people had already come to court
earlier, ואמרי הפיל את שינו וסימא עינו, v'amri hipil es shino v'sima
eino, they said the opposite order, first it was the tooth and
then it was the eye. That was assumed before this other group
came, the opposite order. דבעי מותיב ליה הרב דמי עינו, D'baei mosiv
lei harav dmei eino, the master would have had to free him
and pay him for his eye. ואתו בי תרי מצעי, V'asu bei
trei metzai, then this middle group came, ואמרי לאו עינו והדר שינו,
v'amri lav eino v'hadar shino, no, no, the reverse
order, it was the eye and then the tooth. דלא בעי למיתב
ליה אלא דמי שינו, D'la baei lemeisav lei ela dmei shino, so
they're now helping the master. That's why הרי הרב אומר כן. Harei
harav omer kein. No, no, it was the opposite order and you
only have to pay for the tooth, you don't have to pay
for the eye. They're helping the master and they're hurting the slave.
דקא מכחשי, D'ka machashi, now, but רבא Rava says, so that's got
to be the case, I mean it's a great argument. Okay, but
now the question is, but one minute, if that's true, they came
to court when there was already another testimony in place, their testimony
started off as מוכחשת. mucha-cheshes. Right? The court would have thrown them
both out, or at least they might have not thrown, it's interesting.
Presumably they would have freed the slave, but they wouldn't, you know,
because they're both testifying that the slave goes free, okay, although based
on different circumstances. But presumably they would have thrown out the testimony
about the eye or the tooth because they can't figure out which
one, right? It's another interesting question. Would they have taken the common
denominator of the two, whatever. But anyway, but he's saying look, this
starts as a case of הכחשה. hachasha. Okay, it's actually even more
radical than רבא's Rava, case, because
from the very moment it was testified, it already was facing a
contradictory testimony. And nevertheless,
it is seen as a testimony that then will actually allow for
it to become עדים זוממין edim zomemin afterwards. So you see you
can have הכחשה hachasha that ends in עדים זוממין. edim zomemin. Now,
by the way, I just have to say, not to confuse you,
but it'll come up later. The problem is that עדים only become
עדים זוממין edim zomemin after גמר דין. gmar din. Okay, after the
בית דין Beis Din paskens you're right so-and-so is חייב. chayav. So
in a normal case of רבא, Rava where the הכחשה hachasha comes
later, you could say, they came, they testified X, this person had
committed murder, the court said, okay, we accept the testimony, Reuven is
חייב, chayav, you know, to be executed, he committed murder. And then
it was other witnesses came and contradicted, and then other witnesses came
and made them זוממין. zomemin. So you can have a הכחשה hachasha
and a הזמה hazama that all occurs after the גמר דין, gmar
din, and that's רבא's case, that the הכחשה hachasha doesn't prevent the
הזמה. hazama. But in this case, it's very bizarre. If they started
out with a contradictory testimony, how did you ever get to the
stage of גמר דין gmar din to make them עדים זוממין? edim
zomemin? I really sort of get the problem. Okay, so we're going
to sort of see it in a, we'll discuss that later in
the גמרא. The basic answer is going to be is that they're
testifying that there was another court that had a גמר דין gmar
din about this case. It'll be confusing. But that's tomorrow. Whatever. We'll
worry about that tomorrow. Let's not borrow tomorrow's problems for today. Okay,
but anyway, right, so but anyway,
but that's the point. רש״י Rashi says look, the only way this
makes sense is if there was a backdrop of another testimony and
nevertheless, even though it starts off as contradictory, they're going to be
able to be made עדים זוממים, Eidim Zomemim, so you see הכחשה
תחילת הזמה. Hakhasha Tkhilat Hazama. So the גמרא says אלא דמשכחינן דקא
מסהדי קמאי למציעאי,
Ella demashkhinan deka masahadei
kammaei lemetziai,
the first ones are contradicting the middle ones, and then middle because
last ones that make them זוממים. Zomemim. Okay, והיינו דריש לקיש דאמר
כן, Vehaynu d'Reish Lakish d'amar ken,
that's why the master likes the testimony, דניחא ליה במאי דקאמרי, denikhla
lei bemai deka'amrei,
he likes what they're saying because they're reversing the order, right? So
clearly the other dates had to precede it. ותני ונמצאו זוממים, Vetani
venimtzu zomemim,
and then it says that the middle ones are found זוממים Zomemim
because a later group came, מציעאי משלמי דמי עין לעבד, Metziai meshalmi
dmei ayin le-eved, so the middle ones pay דמי עין לעבד. dmei
ayin le-eved. שמע מינה הכחשה תחילת הזמה, Shma mina Hakhasha Tkhilat Hazama,
you see even though it started off as הכחשה, Hakhasha, it can
still do a process as הזמה Hazama and then they can actually
have to pay. Very nice proof. Let's see what אביי responds. אלא
אביי לא, Ella Abaye lo, no, that's not how to read the
case, דאכחשינהו ואזמינהו. de'achkhishinhu ve'azminhu.
No, no, no, the case is the first ones came and said
here was the order, okay, it was the עין Ayin and then
the שן. Shein. And actually you're right, based on that alone the
master wouldn't be happy, you're making him free his slave and actually
they're hurting the master, they're not hurting the slave. But then the
second group came and said, first of all, עמנו הייתם באותו היום,
Imanu heyitem be-oto hayom, you can't testify, you're זוממים, Zomemim, you were
with us. But if you want to know what happened, what happened
was the opposite order happened. Okay, so this is like really a
fascinating case, right? Because at the time they testified we thought they
were hurting the master, and that, you know, but now, right? Because
nothing had been in court accepted before that. They were telling the
master he had to free his slave. Then they were proven עדים
זוממים Eidim Zomemim and then witnesses said, oh and by the way,
actually the slave should go free but it was the opposite order.
So in hindsight now we see that what they actually were doing
was that they were hurting the slave and not the master. Which
is an interesting question, let's say they didn't know about that other
testimony, right? Is it about what their כוונה Kavana was, who they
were trying to hurt, or was it objectively speaking now that we
know what really happened, we see, you know, maybe that other testimony
never would have been accepted in court. So this is like אביי's
interesting approach that you can testify afterwards to the facts that will
reframe what was the impact of the false testimony of the עדים
זוממים Eidim Zomemim to determine who they have to pay. Okay, and
therefore he says it does not have to start with הכחשה, Hakhasha,
it could start with הזמה Hazama and then you enter the different
testimony into court. Okay, so we'll continue with this tomorrow.